Trying to stay healthy can seem
like a full-time job sometimes.
Especially with all the conflicting
information that’s out there.
But, I’m here to make that job a little easier.
Welcome to the Nutrition Facts podcast,
I’m your host Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that a single dietary change
can increase our resting metabolic rate?
Here’s our story with Nutrition Facts Senior
Research Scientist: Dr. Kristine Dennis.
We now know why fiber-rich foods
can have such a powerful effect
on our weight.
The evidence for the role
of fiber in weight control
started with so-called
ecological studies.
These involve comparing
population averages,
and researchers noted
that populations
with extraordinary fiber intakes
tend to have
negligible obesity rates.
For example, the average
Pima Indian in Mexico
eating their traditional
high-fiber diet
centered around
the "three sisters"
(corn, beans, and squash)
is normal weight,
but the average Pima on U.S.
reservations has obesity.
The problem with dealing
with population averages
is that we don’t know
if the individuals eating
the higher-fiber diets
are themselves necessarily
the ones protected from obesity.
What do we see
in cohort studies,
where individuals and their
diets are followed over time?
A cohort study
of overweight youth found
that the amount of fiber found
in a single half cup
daily serving of beans,
about 6 grams,
over about a two-year period,
was associated
with a profound 25% difference
in abdominal obesity.
In about the same timeframe,
in middle-aged women,
each 2-gram increase
in daily fiber
was associated
with a weight decrease
of about a pound (0.45 kg).
The postpartum period
seems to be a critical time
for women to be
at risk of retaining
the weight put on
during pregnancy.
A study of hundreds of new moms
followed for the first
five months
found that inadequate
fiber intake
appeared to increase
obesity risk by 24%.
And it’s not just women.
A cohort that included
tens of thousands of men
followed for years
concluded that an increase
in fiber consumption
of just 10 grams a day
may prevent about 10% of weight
gain within the population.
Overall, the evidence from these
kinds of observational studies
is strong that
"Increasing consumption
of dietary fiber
with fruits, vegetables,
whole grains, and legumes
across the life cycle
is a critical step in stemming
the epidemic of obesity."
These studies can control
for nondietary influences
such as physical activity
by equipping people with gadgets
to measure their movement,
but there may be uncontrolled
confounding dietary factors.
Think about the list
of high-fiber foods--
fruits, vegetables,
whole grains, and beans.
Maybe fiber intake is just
a marker for the intake
of healthy foods,
and there are dozens of reasons
why eating whole plant foods
could lead to weight loss that
have nothing to do with fiber.
To know if there’s
a cause-and-effect relationship
between fiber and weight loss,
you need to put it to the test
in interventional trials.
That’s where colonic infusions
can come in handy.
In a randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled
crossover study,
researchers showed that people’s
metabolism can be boosted
within 30 minutes of
an infusion into their rectums
of short-chain fatty acids,
the molecules our gut bacteria
make when we feed them fiber.
The study used the amounts
we’d expect to create ourselves
just from eating
a high-fiber diet.
Not only did the study
participants get an increase
in their resting metabolic rate
(the amount of calories burned
just by existing),
but specifically, their fat
oxidation shot up as well,
increasing the amount
of fat they were burning
by more than 25%.
This translates to about
an extra third of a pat
of butter’s worth of fat
burned off their body within
two hours of the infusion.
Colonic catheters aside,
we can get short-chain
fatty acids directly
and get the same little bump
in resting metabolic rate
and whole-body fat breakdown
in addition
to a decrease in appetite.
So again, fiber may work
on both sides
of the energy balance equation.
But does that decreased appetite
actually translate
into eating less?
We’ll find out next.
How does the fiber
we eat in foods
impact our appetites
and our resting metabolic rate,
the amount of calories burned
just by existing?
What happens when we eat
fiber-filled foods like beans?
Researchers in Sweden gave
people beans for supper,
and by the next morning,
after their friendly flora had
a chance to eat them too,
their satiety hormones
like PYY were up,
their hunger hormone ghrelin
was down,
and they reported
feeling less hungry.
The researchers didn’t measure
subsequent food intake,
but a similar study with
whole-grain rye for supper did
and found a decrease in food
intake at lunch the next day.
Those who had eaten the
fiber-rich food the night before
felt fully satiated with about a
hundred fewer calories at a meal
more than 12 hours later.
So, by eating fiber-rich foods,
you’re setting yourself up
for success.
Reduced caloric intake
at a single meal,
or even over a whole day,
doesn’t necessarily translate
into long-term weight loss,
though,
as our body may find
ways of compensating.
Experimentally delivering
short-chain fatty acids
directly to the colon
every day for months
does reduce abdominal fat,
liver fat,
and overall weight gain.
But what about getting them
the old-fashioned way,
eating fiber through our mouth?
A 2022 systematic review
and meta-analysis compilation
of more than two dozen
randomized controlled trials
of various straight fiber
supplements versus placebo
found that those
study participants
in the groups taking
the actual fiber
lost an average of about two
and a half pounds (1.25 kg) more
than those
in the control groups.
These were studies only
averaging 17 weeks long,
though there have been fiber
supplementation trials
that have lasted up to a year,
and they showed
significantly more weight loss.
The fiber supplement findings
were inconsistent, however,
presumably because dozens
of different fiber types
were tested.
How much money can you make
selling beans?
So, there are all sorts of fancy
new fibers on the market
with names like "IQP G-002AS."
(The IQP stands for InQpharm,
the drug company
that came up with it.)
Ironically, it was found
to be quite effective--
according, of course, to the
employees of said drug company,
who published the study.
Using isolated fiber
extracted from plants
or made in a lab
can be helpful in experimentally
proving fiber’s effectiveness
apart from all the other healthy
components in whole foods.
But if anything, one might
expect even greater benefits
from eating fiber
the way nature intended,
in intact plant foods.
It turns out that telling people
to increase their intake
of fiber-rich foods
may actually be
one of the most effective
single pieces of advice
for weight loss.
Published in the prestigious
Annals of Internal Medicine,
a study entitled
"Single-Component Versus
Multicomponent Dietary Goals"
randomly assigned
hundreds of people
into one of two
weight-loss regimens.
One simply encouraged people
to get at least 30 grams
of fiber each day,
which is about the recommended
minimum adequate intake.
The other group was advised
to follow a far more complex
weight-loss program
recommended by
the American Heart Association.
In addition to also
being advised to hit
the 30 daily grams of fiber
target,
study participants
were prescribed
carefully calculated
calorie intake goals,
told to switch
from red meat to white,
cut down on sugary beverages,
reduce sugar and sodium intake
across the board,
and moderate
their alcohol intake.
Even though
both groups were told
to reach the same fiber target,
the group whose sole focus
was fiber intake
ended up eating more than
twice as much extra fiber
as the multicomponent
intervention,
and surprisingly,
similarly improved
the quality of their diets.
So, the fiber-only group
ended up reducing
their saturated fat intake
as much as the group
who was explicitly
instructed to do so.
Just telling people
to eat more whole plant foods
seems by default
to naturally crowd out
some of the less healthy options
that may have ended up
on their plates.
With similar
dietary improvements,
both groups lost
similar amounts of weight,
suggesting if you were able
to give only one piece
of weight-loss advice,
eating more fiber
might not be a bad choice.
Of course, it only works
if you actually do it.
One low-carb study reported
favorable results
compared to a "high-fiber" diet.
How high was this so-called
high-fiber diet?
The study participants
started out
at a terribly low
17.4 grams a day.
Unfortunately, that’s pretty
typical for the United States.
That’s only about half
the average recommended
minimum daily intake
of 31.5 grams.
The human body
was designed to consume
more than 100 grams of fiber
a day.
The participants started out
at 17.4 grams,
and on their "high-fiber" diet,
shot up to 19.7 grams.
That is in no way
a high-fiber diet,
yet the researchers used
their findings to conclude,
"we believe previous claims
of the benefits of fiber
for weight loss
may have been overstated."
Less than 3% of Americans
reach even the recommended
minimum daily
adequate intake of fiber.
There’s so much fuss
about protein,
but for that,
the stats are reversed:
More than 97% of Americans
do get enough protein,
and more than 97% of Americans
do not get enough fiber.
Almost everyone is eating
fiber-deficient diets,
and that’s just based
on the piddly U.S.
dietary recommendations
of 14 grams
per thousand calories,
which comes out to be
about 25 g/day for women
and 38 g/day for men.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to
see all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are available
on each video's page. Information about my books
How Not to Die, How Not to
Diet, and How Not to Age
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a science-based non-profit,
and everything on the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial, not selling anything.
Just put up as a public service, as a labor of
love as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved with
evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.